A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Population Program, Office Files of Michael S. Teitelbaum FA681
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Population Program, Office Files of Michael S. Teitelbaum
1972-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Teitelbaum, Michael S.
Ford Foundation
FA681
5.24 Cubic Feet
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Contains trip files, conference files, subject files, reports and speeches.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series by file type.
The arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Trip and Conference Files, 1972-1980
Series II. Subject Files, 1974-1981
Series III. Reports, Speeches, 1972-1981
Biographical / Historical
Michael Teitelbaum is a demographer, former foundation executive, and educator. He worked at the Ford Foundation during two different stints of time as a Program Officer in the Population Program.
In between his two stints at the Ford Foundation, Teitelbaum worked as a lecturer on demography at Oxford University. He joined the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation in 1983 as a Program Director after his second time at the Ford Foundation and later became Vice President of the organization. Shortly before leaving the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, Teitelbaum became a Wertheim Fellow at Harvard Law School in 2010.
Teitelbaum earned a B.A. in sociology and biology from Reed College and a D.Phil in demography from Oxford University.
- Trip and Conference Files, 1972-1980; I
  - Meeting with Gary Rubin (Institute of Pluralism and Group Identity), 1980 December 23 (Box 1)
  - Abortion Group Meeting, 1980 December 19 (Box 1)
  - Middle East Research Awards Program in Population and Development (MEAWARDS) Meetings (Tunis, Tunisia), 1980 December 11-14 (Box 1)
  - Meeting with S. Waldhorn, 1980 November 21 (Box 1)
  - CICRED Conference (Australia), 1980 November (Box 1)
  - Meeting with Owolabi Re: History of ICH, 1980 November 7 (Box 1)
  - Alan Guttmacher Institute Meeting, 1980 October (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller Foundation -- Meeting on Kenya/Nigeria, 1980 June 5 (Box 1)
  - INS/Border-Crossings Program Discussions (Texas and California), 1980 May 25-31 (Box 1)
  - Federation for American Immigration Reform (FAIR) Meeting, "Illegal Immigration: The Solvable Problem" (Washington, D.C.), 1980 May 23 (Box 1)
  - INS/Immigration Visits (Puerto Rico/Miami), 1980 May 16-21 (Box 1)
  - (Women) Program Implications/1980 Migration Paper Meeting (at the Ford Foundation), 1980 May 16 (Box 1)
  - MST Trip to Washington, D.C. Re: Immigration to the United States, 1980 May 14 (Box 1)
  - Washington, D.C. Trip -- Immigration Meetings, Population, 1980 May 7 (Box 1)
  - Washington, D.C. Trip -- Immigration and Refugees, 1980 April 29 (Box 1)
  - Population Resource Center Briefing (preparation materials), 1980 April 24 (Box 1)
  - American Immigration and Citizenship Conference (Biltmore Hotel, NYC), 1980 April 24 (Box 1)
  - Washington, D.C. Trip, 1980 April 22 (Box 1)
  - The Pathfinder Fund Meetings (Boston, MA), 1980 April 16-18 (Box 1)
  - Population Association of America Annual Meeting (Denver, CO), 1980 April 9-12 (Box 1)
  - U.K. Trip -- IPPF and World Fertility Survey, 1980 March 28-April 5 (Box 1)
  - Migration Conference (Sheraton Centre, NYC), 1980 March 20 (Box 1)
  - In Defense of Aliens (Center for Migration Studies Conference, March 1980) -- Conference Paper Corrections (Box 1)
  - Washington, D.C. Trip -- World Bank Seminar (Reston, VA), 1980 January 16 (Box 1)
  - Overseas Development Council -- Population in the Year 2000, 1979 November 1 (Box 1)
  - India Trip File, 1979 August (Box 1)
  - Sri Lanka Conference File, 1979 August (Box 1)
  - China Population Discussion (Washington, D.C.), 1979 August 7 (Box 1)
  - Africa Trip -- Program Discussion with Ford Foundation Representatives (1/2), 1979 May 20-June 8 (Box 1)
  - Africa Trip -- Program Discussion with Ford Foundation Representatives (2/2), 1979 May 20-June 8 (Box 1)
  - Trip to Tufts University -- World Population, 1975 April 10 (Box 1)
  - UNFPA Meeting Re: Coordination of Population Assistance Projects, 1975 February 20-21 (Box 1)
  - Boston Trip (Nov 7-9, 1974) and Istanbul Trip (Nov 11-13, 1974), 1974 November (Box 1)
  - Japan Trip, 1974 November (Box 1)
  - Conference on Social Science Research on Population and Development (at the Ford Foundation), 1974 October 29-30 (Box 2)
  - Persepolis, Tehran Trip, 1974 June 1-4 (Box 2)
  - Moscow and Iran Trip, 1974 June (Box 2)
  - England Trip, 1973 December 19-1974 January (Box 2)
  - U.K./Europe Trips -- Population Meetings, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
- Subject Files, 1974-1981; II
  - Immigration and Refugees - Meeting to Discuss Report, "A Refugee Education Resource Center in Thailand" (January 18, 1980), 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Meeting on Immigration and Refugees Re: Foundation Wide Immigration Program, 1979 November 20 (Box 2)
  - Immigration and Refugees - Memo (draft), "Impact of Immigration on Size of U.S. Population", 1980 (Box 2)
  - Immigration and Refugees - Migration -- Ford Foundation Materials -- RGAs, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Immigration and Refugees - Migration -- Ford Foundation Materials -- Papers, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Immigration and Refugees - Migration Committee Meeting and Meeting Materials, Grant Proposals (October 9, 1980) (Box 2)
  - Immigration and Refugees - Migration DAP Committee (1/2), 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Immigration and Refugees - Migration DAP Committee (2/2), 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Immigration and Refugees - Migration DAP -- Working File, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Immigration and Refugees - Palmieri, Victor -- Issues Paper Re: Immigration and Refugees (original), 1980 December (Box 2)
  - Immigration and Refugees - Special Foundation Concerns (Ford Foundation) -- Refugees, Indochina, etc., 1979-1981 (Box 2)
  - Immigration and Refugees - United Nations -- Economic Policy Council Panel Session (May 4, 1981) -- Immigration Policy Incl. Teitelbaum Article, "Right vs. Right", 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Abortion Committee -- Memoranda Re: Meetings, Proposals, etc., 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) -- 1981 Symposium (Toronto, Canada) -- "Aging from Birth to Death" -- Michael Teitelbaum Articles and AAAS Report and Revision (Box 3)
  - Asia Population Meeting (Spring 1978) -- Memoranda, Reports, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Fertility, Abortion, Family Planning -- Memoranda, Reports, Proposals, 1979 (Box 3)
  - International Division Reorganization and Management, 1980 (Box 3)
  - International Review Group of Social Science Research on Population and Development (IRG) -- Final Report and Follow-On, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Middle East and Africa (established 12/11/1979) -- Ford Foundation Regional Activities, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
  - Military Task Force -- Memoranda, Reports, Background Papers, Meeting Materials, 1981 (Box 3)
  - PPSO Task Force on the Military and Society, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Population Office -- Budgets (incl. Bellagio background papers and population strategy paper) (1/2), 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - Population Office -- Budgets (incl. Bellagio background papers and population strategy paper) (2/2), 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - RGAs -- Instructions, Program Related Information, etc., 1979-1981 (Box 3)
  - Thomas, Franklin A. -- Memoranda, 1980 December-1981 (Box 3)
  - Trustees Planning Project -- Papers Prepared for the Ford Foundation, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Trustees Planning Project, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Trustees Planning Project -- Incl. "The Hungry, Crowded, Competitive World", 1976 (Box 3)
  - Women in the Military (and W.E.A.L.) -- Proposal and Report, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Women's Project -- Memorandum Re: Project Code, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Women's Programming -- Ford Foundation International Division Activities -- Memoranda, Reports, Proposals, Grant Recommendations (RGAs) (1/4), 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Women's Programming -- Ford Foundation International Division Activities -- Memoranda, Reports, Proposals, Grant Recommendations (RGAs) (2/4), 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - Women's Programming -- Ford Foundation International Division Activities -- Memoranda, Reports, Proposals, Grant Recommendations (RGAs) (3/4), 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - Women's Programming -- Ford Foundation International Division Activities -- Memoranda, Reports, Proposals, Grant Recommendations (RGAs) (4/4), 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - Women's Programming -- Expanded Programs Memorandum and Ford Foundation Division Statements Re: Women's Programs for Board of Trustees Meeting in March, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Women's Program Group -- Meeting Minutes and Notes, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Workshops -- Population Office (Miscellaneous), 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - World Population Year -- Bucharest Conference, 1974 (Box 4)
  - World Population Year -- Bucharest Conference -- "Action Pak", 1974 (Box 4)
- Reports, Speeches, 1972-1981; III
  - Report on Visit to Pakistan (August 14-24, 1972) -- Memorandum from Lyle Saunders, 1972 August 23 (Box 4)
  - Speech Materials (general talk on the Ford Foundation and Population) -- Incl. Ford Foundation Reprint on Population and Development, 1974 (Box 4)
  - "Office for Latin America and the Caribbean Program Review and Funding Request for Fiscal Year 1980-1981", 1979 June (Box 4)
  - "Population in the 1980s" Information Paper, 1979 December (Box 4)
  - "Ford Foundation Programs for Women - An Information Paper for the Board of Trustees", 1979 December (Box 4)
  - "Proposals for General Reserve Funding" for Board of Trustees Meeting, 1980 March 27-28 (Box 4)
  - "Ford Foundation Programs for Women: Plans and Budgets for Fiscal Years 1980-1981", 1980 March (Box 4)
  - "Right vs. Right: Immigration and Refugee Policy in the United States" by Michael S. Teitelbaum, 1980 August 1 (Box 4)
  - "Evaluation of the African American Institute (AAI)" -- Memorandum from Melvin Fox, 1980 August (Box 4)
  - "The Incidence of State and Local Taxes Under Fiscal Change: Methodology" by Dennis de Tray, Prepared by Rand for the Ford Foundation, 1980 August (Box 4)
  - "Exploring a Possible Foundation Program on Nutrition and Related Health Problems", 1980 September (Box 4)
  - "Trends and Prospects in World Population" by Michael Teitelbaum, Prepared for the AAAS Workshop, 1980 November (Box 4)
  - Expanded Programs for Women -- Reports Re: Ford Foundation Women's Programming (incl. reports from National Affairs Program and Education and Public Policy), 1980 (Box 4)
  - "The Demographic Impact of Tubectomy in Bangladesh" by Anthony R. Measham, et al., circa 1980 (Box 4)
  - Nutrition/Health Paper, "Child Survival: A Fair Start for Children", 1981 April 15 (Box 4)
  - "Fiscal Restraints and the Burden of Local and State Taxes" Prepared by Rand for the Ford Foundation, 1981 April (Box 4)
  - Ford Foundation Division/Program Concept Papers (Youth, Education, International Affairs, Human Rights and Justice, Governance and Public Policy), 1981 (Box 4)
  - "The Hungry, Crowded, Competitive World - Analytic Commentary" by Michael S. Teitelbaum, et al., undated (Box 4)